<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-16"?>
<leg xml:space="preserve" billnum="SJR006" sponsor="Scott D. Sandall" designation="SJR" otherSponsor="" otherHouse="House" sess="2026GS" fileno="2026FL0266" date="1/16/2026 13:01:227" printDate="01-16 13:58" subVer="0" minVer="0" office="LEGISLATIVE GENERAL COUNSEL" actionDate="" impact="reso"><info><nextbuid>4</nextbuid><aminfo anum="0" effdate="01/01/1800"><seclist><sect src="uncod" untype="rule" buid="2" uid="URV00000042" sort="URV00042" mtype="section" atype="A" effdate="01/01/1800">Rule 42</sect><sect src="uncod" untype="effdate" buid="3" uid="EF0000" sort="UZEFF" mtype="uncod" effdate="01/01/1800"/></seclist></aminfo></info><tbox><sinfo><nextpairid>0</nextpairid></sinfo><st numlevel="1" lineno="1" slineno="0-1">Joint Resolution Amending Court Rules Regarding Medical Malpractice</st><sessionhead>2026 GENERAL SESSION</sessionhead><statehead>STATE OF UTAH</statehead><sponsorhead>Chief Sponsor: Scott D. Sandall</sponsorhead><otherSponsorhead>House Sponsor: </otherSponsorhead></tbox><lt numlevel="1" lineno="2" slineno="0-2"><lthead lineno="3">LONG TITLE</lthead><gdhead lineno="4">General Description:</gdhead><gd numlevel="1" lineno="5" slineno="0-5">This resolution amends court rules to address medical malpractice actions. </gd><hphead lineno="6">Highlighted Provisions:</hphead><hp numlevel="1" lineno="7" slineno="0-7">This resolution:<hl numlevel="1" lineno="8" slineno="0-8" level="1">amends Rule 42 of the Utah Rules of Civil Procedure to address separate trials in a <ln numlevel="1" lineno="9" slineno="0-9"/>medical malpractice action; and</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="10" slineno="0-10" level="1">makes technical and conforming changes.</hl></hp><moni numlevel="1" lineno="11" slineno="0-11" display="none">Money Appropriated in this Bill:</moni><moniNone lineno="12">None</moniNone><oc numlevel="1" lineno="13" slineno="0-13">Other Special Clauses:<ocl type="effdate" sort="2" numlevel="1" lineno="14" slineno="0-14">This resolution provides a special effective date.</ocl></oc><pa type="civil" numlevel="1" lineno="15" slineno="0-15">Utah Rules of Civil Procedure Affected:<paamd numlevel="1" lineno="16" slineno="0-16"><snhead>AMENDS:</snhead><sn num="Rule 42" src="uncod" uid="URV00000042" buid="2" sort="URV00042" numlevel="1" lineno="17" slineno="0-17"><bold>Rule 42</bold>, Utah Rules of Civil Procedure</sn></paamd></pa></lt><enacthead lineno="18"/><enact numlevel="1" lineno="19" slineno="0-19">Be it resolved by the Legislature of the state of Utah, two-thirds of all members elected to each <ln numlevel="1" lineno="20" slineno="0-20"/>of the two houses voting in favor thereof:<enactdesc numlevel="1" lineno="21" slineno="0-21">As provided in Utah Constitution Article VIII, Section 4, the Legislature may amend rules of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="22" slineno="0-22"/>procedure and evidence adopted by the Utah Supreme Court upon a two-thirds vote of all <ln numlevel="1" lineno="23" slineno="0-23"/>members of both houses of the Legislature:</enactdesc></enact><bdy><bsec buid="2" type="uncod" untype="rule" rtype="civil" atype="amend" num="Rule 42" src="rule" uid="URV00000042" sort="URV00042" langlock="false" numlevel="1" lineno="24" slineno="1-1" sn="1"><section number="Rule 42" numlevel="1" lineno="25" slineno="1-2" type="uncod" untype="rule" atype="amend"><secline lineno="24">Section 1. <bold>Rule 42</bold>, Utah Rules of Civil Procedure is amended to read:</secline><catline lineno="25"><bold>Rule 42<parens/>. Consolidation; separate trials; venue transfer.</bold></catline><sectionText lineno="26"><tab/><bold>(a) Consolidation.</bold> When actions involving a common question of law or fact or arising <ln numlevel="1" lineno="27" slineno="1-4"/>from the same transaction or occurrence are pending before the court in one or more judicial <ln numlevel="1" lineno="28" slineno="1-5"/>districts, the court may, on motion of any party or on the court's own initiative: order that the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="29" slineno="1-6"/>actions are consolidated in whole or in part for any purpose, including for discovery, other <ln numlevel="1" lineno="30" slineno="1-7"/>pretrial matters, or a joint hearing or trial; stay any or all of the proceedings in any action <ln numlevel="1" lineno="31" slineno="1-8"/>subject to the order; transfer any or all further proceedings in the actions to a location in which <ln numlevel="1" lineno="32" slineno="1-9"/>any of the actions is pending after consulting with the presiding judge of the transferee court; <ln numlevel="1" lineno="33" slineno="1-10"/>and make other such orders concerning proceedings therein as may tend to avoid unnecessary <ln numlevel="1" lineno="34" slineno="1-11"/>costs or delay.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="35" slineno="1-12" display="tab"/><para/>(1) In determining whether to order consolidation and the appropriate location for the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="36" slineno="1-13"/>consolidated proceedings, the court may consider, among other factors: the complexity of the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="37" slineno="1-14"/>actions; the importance of any common question of fact or law to the determination of the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="38" slineno="1-15"/>actions; the risk of duplicative or inconsistent rulings, orders, or judgments; the relative <ln numlevel="1" lineno="39" slineno="1-16"/>procedural postures of the actions; the risk that consolidation may unreasonably delay the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="40" slineno="1-17"/>progress, increase the expense, or complicate the processing of any action; prejudice to any <ln numlevel="1" lineno="41" slineno="1-18"/>party that far outweighs the overall benefits of consolidation; the convenience of the parties, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="42" slineno="1-19"/>witnesses, and counsel; and the efficient utilization of judicial resources and the facilities and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="43" slineno="1-20"/>personnel of the court.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="44" slineno="1-21" display="tab"/><para/>(2) A motion to consolidate may be filed or opposed by any party. The motion must be <ln numlevel="1" lineno="45" slineno="1-22"/>filed in and heard by the judge assigned to the first action filed and must be served on all <ln numlevel="1" lineno="46" slineno="1-23"/>parties in each action pursuant to Rule 5. A notice of the motion must be filed in each action. <ln numlevel="1" lineno="47" slineno="1-24"/>The movant must, and any party may, file in each action notice of the order denying or <ln numlevel="1" lineno="48" slineno="1-25"/>granting the motion. <eol numlevel="1" lineno="49" slineno="1-26" display="tab"/><para/>(3) If the court orders consolidation, a new case number will be used for all subsequent <ln numlevel="1" lineno="50" slineno="1-27"/>filings in the consolidated case. The court may direct that specified parties pay the expenses, if <ln numlevel="1" lineno="51" slineno="1-28"/>any, of consolidation. The presiding judge of the transferee court may assign the consolidated <ln numlevel="1" lineno="52" slineno="1-29"/>case to another judge for good cause.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="53" slineno="1-30" display="tab"/><bold>(b) Separate trials.</bold> <amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="1" groupid="1" style="1" owner="jchristopherson" level="1" amendtag="both"><eol numlevel="1" lineno="54" slineno="1-31" display="tab"/><para/>(1) </amend><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="5" groupid="5" style="2" owner="jchristopherson" level="1" deltag="both">The</amend><amendoutend style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="4" groupid="4" style="1" owner="jchristopherson" level="1" amendtag="both" space="true">Except as provided in paragraph (b)(2), the</amend> court in furtherance of convenience <ln numlevel="1" lineno="55" slineno="1-32"/>or to avoid prejudice may order a separate trial of any claim, cross claim, counterclaim, or <ln numlevel="1" lineno="56" slineno="1-33"/>third party claim, or of any separate issue or of any number of claims, cross claims, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="57" slineno="1-34"/>counterclaims, third party claims, or issues.<amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="3" groupid="3" style="1" owner="jchristopherson" level="1" amendtag="both"><eol numlevel="1" lineno="58" slineno="1-35" display="tab"/><para/>(2) For a malpractice action against a health care provider, and upon a motion by a party, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="59" slineno="1-36"/>the court shall order:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="60" slineno="1-37" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(A) a separate trial to be held to determine the liability of the defendant; and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="61" slineno="1-38" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(B) a separate trial to be held to determine the amount of damages owed by the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="62" slineno="1-39"/>defendant after liability of the defendant is established.<tab/></amend><eol numlevel="1" lineno="63" slineno="1-40" display="tab"/><bold>(c) Venue Transfer.</bold><eol numlevel="1" lineno="64" slineno="1-41" display="tab"/><para/>(1) On timely motion of any party, where transfer to a proper venue is available, the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="65" slineno="1-42"/>court must transfer any action filed in an improper venue.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="66" slineno="1-43" display="tab"/><para/>(2) The court must give substantial deference to a plaintiff's choice of a proper venue. <ln numlevel="1" lineno="67" slineno="1-44"/>On timely motion of any party, a court may: transfer venue of any action, in whole or in part, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="68" slineno="1-45"/>to any other venue for any purpose, including for discovery, other pretrial matters, or a joint <ln numlevel="1" lineno="69" slineno="1-46"/>hearing or trial; stay any or all of the proceedings in the action; and make other such orders <ln numlevel="1" lineno="70" slineno="1-47"/>concerning proceedings therein to pursue the interests of justice and avoid unnecessary costs <ln numlevel="1" lineno="71" slineno="1-48"/>or delay. In determining whether to transfer venue and the appropriate venue for the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="72" slineno="1-49"/>transferred proceedings, the court may consider, among other factors, whether transfer will: <ln numlevel="1" lineno="73" slineno="1-50"/>increase the likelihood of a fair and impartial determination in the action; minimize expense or <ln numlevel="1" lineno="74" slineno="1-51"/>inconvenience to parties, witnesses, or the court; decrease delay; avoid hardship or injustice <ln numlevel="1" lineno="75" slineno="1-52"/>otherwise caused by venue requirements; and advance the interests of justice. <eol numlevel="1" lineno="76" slineno="1-53" display="tab"/><para/>(3) The court may direct that specified parties pay the expenses, if any, of transfer.<bold/></sectionText></section></bsec><bsec buid="3" type="uncod" untype="effdate" src="uncod" uid="EF0000" sort="UZEFF" langlock="false" numlevel="1" lineno="77" slineno="2-1" sn="2"><section type="uncod" untype="effdate" display="false" src="uncod"><secline lineno="77">Section 2.  <bold>Effective Date.</bold></secline><sectionText lineno="78"><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="3" groupid="3" style="1" owner="jchristopherson" level="1" amendtag="both">As provided in Utah Constitution, Article VIII, Section 4, this resolution takes effect <ln numlevel="1" lineno="79" slineno="2-3"/>upon a two-thirds vote of all members elected to each house.</amend></sectionText></section></bsec></bdy><foot><rev><tm>1-16-26 1:58 PM</tm></rev></foot></leg>