<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-16"?>
<leg xml:space="preserve" billnum="SCR001" sponsor="Derrin R. Owens" designation="SCR" otherSponsor="Colin W. Jack" otherHouse="House" sess="2026GS" fileno="2026FL0737" date="12/23/2025 12:12:77" printDate="12-23 12:55" subVer="0" minVer="0" office="LEGISLATIVE GENERAL COUNSEL" actionDate="" impact="reso"><info><nextbuid>2</nextbuid><aminfo anum="0" effdate="01/01/1800"><seclist><sect action="E" src="reso" buid="1" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" mtype="section" effdate="01/01/1800"/></seclist></aminfo></info><tbox><sinfo><nextpairid>0</nextpairid></sinfo><st numlevel="1" lineno="1" slineno="0-1">Concurrent Resolution Regarding Nuclear Energy</st><sessionhead>2026 GENERAL SESSION</sessionhead><statehead>STATE OF UTAH</statehead><sponsorhead>Chief Sponsor: Derrin R. Owens</sponsorhead><otherSponsorhead>House Sponsor: Colin W. Jack</otherSponsorhead></tbox><lt numlevel="1" lineno="2" slineno="0-2"><lthead lineno="3">LONG TITLE</lthead><cn numlevel="1" lineno="4" slineno="0-4">Committee Note:<comrec voteid="38308" comcode="INTPUT" numlevel="1" lineno="5" slineno="0-5"> The Public Utilities, Energy, and Technology Interim Committee recommended this bill.<legvote numlevel="1" lineno="6" slineno="0-6">Legislative Vote:<yes>13 voting for</yes><no>0 voting against</no><abs>5 absent</abs></legvote></comrec></cn><gdhead lineno="7">General Description:</gdhead><gd numlevel="1" lineno="8" slineno="0-8">This resolution expresses support and intent for Utah to pursue Agreement State status with <ln numlevel="1" lineno="9" slineno="0-9"/>the Nuclear Regulatory Commission for additional elements of the nuclear fuel cycle. </gd><hphead lineno="10">Highlighted Provisions:</hphead><hp numlevel="1" lineno="11" slineno="0-11">This resolution:<hl numlevel="1" lineno="12" slineno="0-12" level="1">highlights Utah's support for nuclear energy development and deployment; and</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="13" slineno="0-13" level="1">expresses Utah's intent to pursue agreement state status for additional elements of the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="14" slineno="0-14"/>nuclear fuel cycle.</hl></hp><moni numlevel="1" lineno="15" slineno="0-15" display="none">Money Appropriated in this Bill:</moni><moniNone lineno="16">None</moniNone><oc numlevel="1" lineno="17" slineno="0-17">Other Special Clauses:</oc><ocNone lineno="18">None</ocNone></lt><enacthead lineno="19"/><enact numlevel="1" lineno="20" slineno="0-20">Be it resolved by the Legislature of the state of Utah, the Governor concurring therein:</enact><bdy><bsec buid="1" type="enact" src="reso" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" numlevel="1" lineno="21" slineno="1-1" sn="1"><section type="enact" display="false" src="reso"><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="1" groupid="1" style="X" owner="ahaskell" level="1" amendtag="both">WHEREAS, under Section 274 of the Atomic Energy Act, 42 U.S.C. Sec. 2021, the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="22" slineno="1-2"/>Nuclear Regulatory Commission is authorized to enter into agreements with states to assume <ln numlevel="1" lineno="23" slineno="1-3"/>regulatory authority over certain nuclear materials and activities;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="24" slineno="1-4" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, Utah desires to expand its regulatory authority to include elements of the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="25" slineno="1-5"/>nuclear fuel cycle that are not prohibited by federal statute;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="26" slineno="1-6" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, increased state participation in these regulatory areas would enhance local <ln numlevel="1" lineno="27" slineno="1-7"/>oversight, improve coordination with industry and federal partners, and support Utah's broader <ln numlevel="1" lineno="28" slineno="1-8"/>energy development goals;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="29" slineno="1-9" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, certain elements of the nuclear fuel cycle may be appropriate for state <ln numlevel="1" lineno="30" slineno="1-10"/>management;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="31" slineno="1-11" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, Utah intends to work collaboratively with the Nuclear Regulatory <ln numlevel="1" lineno="32" slineno="1-12"/>Commission to develop the technical, legal, and administrative framework necessary to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="33" slineno="1-13"/>support an Agreement State application for additional eligible portions of the fuel cycle;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="34" slineno="1-14" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the governor, through the support and facilitation of the Division of Waste <ln numlevel="1" lineno="35" slineno="1-15"/>Management and Radiation Control, may submit a letter of intent to the Nuclear Regulatory <ln numlevel="1" lineno="36" slineno="1-16"/>Commission to begin the process toward establishing that status; and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="37" slineno="1-17" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the Legislature recognizes the importance of maintaining high standards for <ln numlevel="1" lineno="38" slineno="1-18"/>nuclear safety and environmental protection while enabling states to participate responsibly in <ln numlevel="1" lineno="39" slineno="1-19"/>regulatory oversight:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="40" slineno="1-20" display="tab"/>NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED that the Legislature of the state of Utah <ln numlevel="1" lineno="41" slineno="1-21"/>expresses intent to pursue Agreement State status for elements of the nuclear fuel cycle not <ln numlevel="1" lineno="42" slineno="1-22"/>expressly prohibited and encourages the Nuclear Regulatory Commission to clarify which <ln numlevel="1" lineno="43" slineno="1-23"/>portions of the fuel cycle are reserved by statute versus policy.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="44" slineno="1-24" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that the Legislature supports the governor and the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="45" slineno="1-25"/>Department of Environmental Quality in coordinating with the Nuclear Regulatory <ln numlevel="1" lineno="46" slineno="1-26"/>Commission to initiate the Agreement State application process for eligible activities.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="47" slineno="1-27" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that copies of this resolution be sent to the chairman of the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="48" slineno="1-28"/>Nuclear Regulatory Commission, the governor of Utah, and Utah's congressional delegation.</amend><sectionText/></section></bsec></bdy><foot><rev><tm>12-23-25 12:55 PM</tm></rev></foot></leg>