<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-16"?>
<leg xml:space="preserve" billnum="HCR006" sponsor="Stephen L. Whyte" designation="HCR" otherSponsor="Lincoln Fillmore" otherHouse="Senate" sess="2026GS" fileno="2026FL1258" date="01-19-26" printDate="01-19 18:52" subVer="0" minVer="0" office="LEGISLATIVE GENERAL COUNSEL" actionDate="" impact="reso"><info><nextbuid>2</nextbuid><aminfo anum="0" effdate="01/01/1800"><seclist><sect action="E" src="reso" buid="1" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" mtype="section" effdate="01/01/1800"/></seclist></aminfo></info><tbox><sinfo/><st numlevel="1" lineno="1" slineno="0-1">Concurrent Resolution Regarding the Utah Housing Strategic Plan</st><sessionhead>2026 GENERAL SESSION</sessionhead><statehead>STATE OF UTAH</statehead><sponsorhead>Chief Sponsor: Stephen L. Whyte</sponsorhead><otherSponsorhead>Senate Sponsor: Lincoln Fillmore</otherSponsorhead></tbox><lt numlevel="1" lineno="2" slineno="0-2"><lthead lineno="3">LONG TITLE</lthead><gdhead lineno="4">General Description:</gdhead><gd numlevel="1" lineno="5" slineno="0-5">This resolution supports the implementation of the Utah Housing Strategic Plan. </gd><hphead lineno="6">Highlighted Provisions:</hphead><hp numlevel="1" lineno="7" slineno="0-7">This resolution:<hl numlevel="1" lineno="8" slineno="0-8" level="1">finds the lack of alignment and coordination among government agencies causes housing <ln numlevel="1" lineno="9" slineno="0-9"/>development delays and increased housing costs;</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="10" slineno="0-10" level="1">supports implementing the Utah Housing Strategic Plan; and</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="11" slineno="0-11" level="1">commits to track implementation and results of the Utah Housing Strategic Plan.</hl></hp><moni numlevel="1" lineno="12" slineno="0-12" display="none">Money Appropriated in this Bill:</moni><moniNone lineno="13">None</moniNone><oc numlevel="1" lineno="14" slineno="0-14">Other Special Clauses:</oc><ocNone lineno="15">None</ocNone></lt><enacthead lineno="16"/><enact numlevel="1" lineno="17" slineno="0-17">Be it resolved by the Legislature of the state of Utah, the Governor concurring therein:</enact><bdy><bsec buid="1" type="enact" src="reso" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" numlevel="1" lineno="18" slineno="1-1" sn="1"><section type="enact" display="false" src="reso"><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="1" groupid="1" style="X" owner="jchristopherson" level="1" amendtag="both">WHEREAS, Utah is one of the fastest growing states, by population, in the United States;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="19" slineno="1-2" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, this rapid population growth has significantly increased the demand for <ln numlevel="1" lineno="20" slineno="1-3"/>housing across all income levels and regions of the state;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="21" slineno="1-4" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the Kem C. Gardner Policy Institute and the Office of the Legislator Auditor <ln numlevel="1" lineno="22" slineno="1-5"/>General identified a persistent and growing gap between housing supply and housing demand, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="23" slineno="1-6"/>which contributes to rising home purchasing prices;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="24" slineno="1-7" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, high housing costs negatively impact workforce recruitment, economic <ln numlevel="1" lineno="25" slineno="1-8"/>competitiveness, and quality of life for Utah businesses and residents;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="26" slineno="1-9" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, housing assistance programs, economic incentive programs, and housing <ln numlevel="1" lineno="27" slineno="1-10"/>planning initiatives exist within multiple government agencies resulting in housing <ln numlevel="1" lineno="28" slineno="1-11"/>development delays and subsequently, increased housing costs;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="29" slineno="1-12" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, a comprehensive statewide housing strategy is needed to align land use, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="30" slineno="1-13"/>infrastructure investment, transportation planning, and economic development goals to meet <ln numlevel="1" lineno="31" slineno="1-14"/>Utah's housing needs;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="32" slineno="1-15" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, during the 2025 General Session, H.C.R.14, House Concurrent Resolution <ln numlevel="1" lineno="33" slineno="1-16"/>Supporting Streamlining Utah Housing Policies, recommended streamlining and consolidating <ln numlevel="1" lineno="34" slineno="1-17"/>Utah's housing programs to increase alignment and coordination among governmental entities;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="35" slineno="1-18" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, H.B. 37, Utah Housing Amendments, from the 2025 General Session required <ln numlevel="1" lineno="36" slineno="1-19"/>the Governor's Office of Planning and Budget to develop a state housing plan no later than <ln numlevel="1" lineno="37" slineno="1-20"/>December 31, 2025; and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="38" slineno="1-21" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the Governor's Office of Planning and Budget, in partnership with more than <ln numlevel="1" lineno="39" slineno="1-22"/>100 stakeholders, including legislators, completed the development of the Utah Housing <ln numlevel="1" lineno="40" slineno="1-23"/>Strategic Plan that outlines Utah's housing goals and includes guiding principles, outcome <ln numlevel="1" lineno="41" slineno="1-24"/>metrics, and recommendations to meet Utah's housing needs:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="42" slineno="1-25" display="tab"/>NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED that the Legislature of the state of Utah, the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="43" slineno="1-26"/>Governor concurring therein, finds a lack of alignment and coordination among government <ln numlevel="1" lineno="44" slineno="1-27"/>agencies causes housing development delays and increased housing costs, which adversely <ln numlevel="1" lineno="45" slineno="1-28"/>affect Utah's economic growth and quality of life.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="46" slineno="1-29" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that the Legislature and the Governor support <ln numlevel="1" lineno="47" slineno="1-30"/>implementing the Utah Housing Strategic Plan to align and coordinate statewide efforts to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="48" slineno="1-31"/>increase housing supply and improve affordability.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="49" slineno="1-32" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that the Legislature and the Governor commit to track the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="50" slineno="1-33"/>Utah Housing Strategic Plan implementation and results to ensure the plan remains responsive <ln numlevel="1" lineno="51" slineno="1-34"/>to Utah's changing housing needs.</amend><sectionText/></section></bsec></bdy><foot><rev><tm>1-19-26 1:31 PM</tm></rev></foot></leg>