<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-16"?>
<leg xml:space="preserve" billnum="HJR029" sponsor="Jason E. Thompson" designation="HJR" otherSponsor="" otherHouse="Senate" subNumber="01" subSponsor="Jason E. Thompson" sess="2026GS" fileno="2026FL1506" date="2/19/2026 18:02:757" printDate="02-19 18:34" subVer="1" minVer="0" office="LEGISLATIVE GENERAL COUNSEL" actionDate="" impact="reso"><info><nextbuid>2</nextbuid><aminfo anum="0" effdate="01/01/1800"><seclist><sect action="E" src="reso" buid="1" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" mtype="section" effdate="01/01/1800"/></seclist></aminfo></info><tbox><sinfo><nextpairid>0</nextpairid></sinfo><st numlevel="1" lineno="1" slineno="0-1">Resolution in Support of the Upward Mobility Act</st><sessionhead>2026 GENERAL SESSION</sessionhead><statehead>STATE OF UTAH</statehead><sponsorhead>Chief Sponsor: Jason E. Thompson</sponsorhead><otherSponsorhead>Senate Sponsor: </otherSponsorhead></tbox><lt numlevel="1" lineno="2" slineno="0-2"><lthead lineno="3">LONG TITLE</lthead><gdhead lineno="4">General Description:</gdhead><gd numlevel="1" lineno="5" slineno="0-5">This resolution proclaims that the Legislature of the state of Utah supports the enactment of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="6" slineno="0-6"/>the Upward Mobility Act by the United States Congress.</gd><hphead lineno="7">Highlighted Provisions:</hphead><hp numlevel="1" lineno="8" slineno="0-8">This resolution:<hl numlevel="1" lineno="9" slineno="0-9" level="1">highlights Utah's achievements as the state with the most upward mobility;</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="10" slineno="0-10" level="1">urges the passage and implementation of the Upward Mobility Act (Act) by the United <ln numlevel="1" lineno="11" slineno="0-11"/>States Congress; and</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="12" slineno="0-12" level="1">volunteers Utah to participate in the pilot program created by the Act.</hl></hp><moni numlevel="1" lineno="13" slineno="0-13" display="none">Money Appropriated in this Bill:</moni><moniNone lineno="14">None</moniNone><oc numlevel="1" lineno="15" slineno="0-15">Other Special Clauses:</oc><ocNone lineno="16">None</ocNone></lt><enacthead lineno="17"/><enact numlevel="1" lineno="18" slineno="0-18">Be it resolved by the Legislature of the state of Utah:</enact><bdy><bsec buid="1" type="enact" src="reso" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" numlevel="1" lineno="19" slineno="1-1" sn="1"><section type="enact" display="false" src="reso"><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="1" groupid="1" style="X" owner="jchristopherson" level="1" amendtag="both">WHEREAS, according to the Archbridge Institute, Utah is ranked number one in the nation <ln numlevel="1" lineno="20" slineno="1-2"/>for upward mobility;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="21" slineno="1-3" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, upward mobility allows an individual to escape poverty and achieve financial <ln numlevel="1" lineno="22" slineno="1-4"/>independence;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="23" slineno="1-5" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, programs intending to reduce poverty, such as the Supplemental Nutrition <ln numlevel="1" lineno="24" slineno="1-6"/>Assistance Program (SNAP), Temporary Assistance for Needy Families (TANF), and Section <ln numlevel="1" lineno="25" slineno="1-7"/>8 Tenant-Based Rental Assistance, are primarily administered by the federal government of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="26" slineno="1-8"/>the United States of America;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="27" slineno="1-9" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, these programs are meant to assist low income individuals and families to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="28" slineno="1-10"/>raise them from poverty through food, housing, and economic assistance;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="29" slineno="1-11" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, inflexible income requirements for assistance create perceived or real <ln numlevel="1" lineno="30" slineno="1-12"/>"benefits cliffs" where an increase in income can create a significant loss in assistance;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="31" slineno="1-13" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, benefits cliffs can harm individuals receiving benefits and prevent the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="32" slineno="1-14"/>reduction of poverty;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="33" slineno="1-15" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, Representative Blake Moore of Utah introduced the Upward Mobility Act of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="34" slineno="1-16"/>2026 (Act) to the 119th Congress of the United States;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="35" slineno="1-17" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the Act is a bipartisan initiative aimed at reforming federal anti-poverty <ln numlevel="1" lineno="36" slineno="1-18"/>programs and eliminating benefits cliffs;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="37" slineno="1-19" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the Act, if passed, will create a five-year pilot program for up to five states to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="38" slineno="1-20"/>receive an "Upward Mobility Grant" to administer the pilot program;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="39" slineno="1-21" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, Upward Mobility Grants combine funding from 10 anti-poverty programs into <ln numlevel="1" lineno="40" slineno="1-22"/>a single block grant;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="41" slineno="1-23" display="tab"/>WHEREAS. states participating in the pilot program can request waivers from the federal <ln numlevel="1" lineno="42" slineno="1-24"/>government to design programs that promote self-sufficiency;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="43" slineno="1-25" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the United States Department of Health and Human Services' Administration <ln numlevel="1" lineno="44" slineno="1-26"/>for Children and Families will oversee the pilot program and select state proposals that <ln numlevel="1" lineno="45" slineno="1-27"/>demonstrate potential in removing benefits cliffs to aid individuals in achieving financial <ln numlevel="1" lineno="46" slineno="1-28"/>independence; and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="47" slineno="1-29" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, participating in the pilot program includes rigorous independent evaluations to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="48" slineno="1-30"/>measure the impact on employment, earnings, and poverty reduction:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="49" slineno="1-31" display="tab"/>NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED that the Legislature of the state of Utah supports <ln numlevel="1" lineno="50" slineno="1-32"/>the passage and implementation of Representative Blake Moore's Upward Mobility Act of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="51" slineno="1-33"/>2026.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="52" slineno="1-34" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that the Legislature recognizes that the state's success in <ln numlevel="1" lineno="53" slineno="1-35"/>enhancing upward mobility makes Utah an obvious choice to participate in the pilot program <ln numlevel="1" lineno="54" slineno="1-36"/>created by the Upward Mobility Act.</amend><sectionText/></section></bsec></bdy><foot><rev><tm>2-19-26 6:34 PM</tm></rev></foot></leg>