<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-16"?>
<leg xml:space="preserve" billnum="HCR008" sponsor="Stewart E. Barlow" designation="HCR" otherSponsor="Daniel McCay" otherHouse="Senate" subNumber="01" subSponsor="Stewart E. Barlow" sess="2026GS" fileno="2026FL1313" date="2/20/2026 10:02:207" printDate="02-23 11:05" subVer="1" minVer="0" office="LEGISLATIVE GENERAL COUNSEL" actionDate="" impact="reso"><info><nextbuid>2</nextbuid><aminfo anum="0" effdate="01/01/1800"><seclist><sect action="E" src="reso" buid="1" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" mtype="section" effdate="01/01/1800"/></seclist></aminfo></info><tbox><sinfo><nextpairid>0</nextpairid></sinfo><st numlevel="1" lineno="1" slineno="0-1">Concurrent Resolution Directing PEHP to Establish the Weight Management and Obesity Pilot Program</st><sessionhead>2026 GENERAL SESSION</sessionhead><statehead>STATE OF UTAH</statehead><sponsorhead>Chief Sponsor: Stewart E. Barlow</sponsorhead><otherSponsorhead>Senate Sponsor: Daniel McCay</otherSponsorhead></tbox><lt numlevel="1" lineno="2" slineno="0-2"><lthead lineno="3">LONG TITLE</lthead><gdhead lineno="4">General Description:</gdhead><gd numlevel="1" lineno="5" slineno="0-5">This resolution directs the Public Employees' Benefit Insurance Program to establish the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="6" slineno="0-6"/>Weight Management and Obesity Pilot Program.</gd><hphead lineno="7">Highlighted Provisions:</hphead><hp numlevel="1" lineno="8" slineno="0-8">This resolution:<hl numlevel="1" lineno="9" slineno="0-9" level="1">recognizes the existing bariatric surgery pilot program within the Public Employees' <ln numlevel="1" lineno="10" slineno="0-10"/>Benefit Insurance Program (PEHP); and</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="11" slineno="0-11" level="1">directs PEHP to establish a new Weight Management and Obesity Pilot Program that <ln numlevel="1" lineno="12" slineno="0-12"/>combines the bariatric surgery pilot program with an option for GLP-1 coverage.</hl></hp><moni numlevel="1" lineno="13" slineno="0-13" display="none">Money Appropriated in this Bill:</moni><moniNone lineno="14">None</moniNone><oc numlevel="1" lineno="15" slineno="0-15">Other Special Clauses:</oc><ocNone lineno="16">None</ocNone></lt><enacthead lineno="17"/><enact numlevel="1" lineno="18" slineno="0-18">Be it resolved by the Legislature of the state of Utah, the Governor concurring therein:</enact><bdy><bsec buid="1" type="enact" src="reso" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" numlevel="1" lineno="19" slineno="1-1" sn="1"><section type="enact" display="false" src="reso"><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="1" groupid="1" style="X" owner="jchristopherson" level="1" amendtag="both">WHEREAS, in accordance with Utah Code Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="49-20-201">49-20-201</xref>, the state participates in the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="20" slineno="1-2"/>Public Employees' Benefit Insurance Program (PEHP);<eol numlevel="1" lineno="21" slineno="1-3" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the state has authorized PEHP since 2011 to administer a pilot program for <ln numlevel="1" lineno="22" slineno="1-4"/>bariatric surgery for the state health insurance plan with an adjusted annual budget of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="23" slineno="1-5"/>$1,050,000;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="24" slineno="1-6" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, a member must, among other things, meet medical criteria of over 40 BMI or <ln numlevel="1" lineno="25" slineno="1-7"/>over 35 BMI with certain comorbidities, participate in health coaching, and show an aptitude <ln numlevel="1" lineno="26" slineno="1-8"/>for weight loss over six months to qualify for the bariatric surgery pilot program;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="27" slineno="1-9" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, data suggests that the class of drugs known as glucagon-like peptide-1 <ln numlevel="1" lineno="28" slineno="1-10"/>receptor agonists, known as GLP-1 drugs, could be an effective option for medically qualified <ln numlevel="1" lineno="29" slineno="1-11"/>members;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="30" slineno="1-12" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, PEHP currently provides coverage for GLP-1 drugs for diabetes treatment, but <ln numlevel="1" lineno="31" slineno="1-13"/>does not cover GLP-1 drugs for obesity treatment; and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="32" slineno="1-14" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the state desires to make available an alternative GLP-1 benefit for medically <ln numlevel="1" lineno="33" slineno="1-15"/>qualified members that would be limited in scope to stay within the adjusted budget of the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="34" slineno="1-16"/>bariatric surgery pilot program:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="35" slineno="1-17" display="tab"/>NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED that the Legislature of the state of Utah, the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="36" slineno="1-18"/>Governor concurring therein, directs the Public Employees' Benefit Insurance Program, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="37" slineno="1-19"/>beginning with the 2026 plan year, to:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="38" slineno="1-20" display="tab"/>(1) modify the current bariatric surgery pilot program to be the 'Weight Management and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="39" slineno="1-21"/>Obesity Pilot Program' and include an alternative GLP-1 treatment pathway;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="40" slineno="1-22" display="tab"/>(2) define the parameters of the alternative GLP-1 treatment pathway for medically <ln numlevel="1" lineno="41" slineno="1-23"/>qualified members, including requirements that the program:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="42" slineno="1-24" display="tab"/><para/>a. be administered on a reimbursement basis;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="43" slineno="1-25" display="tab"/><para/>b. include 50% member cost sharing;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="44" slineno="1-26" display="tab"/><para/>c. cap monthly PEHP allowed pharmacy expenses at $300 per member;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="45" slineno="1-27" display="tab"/><para/>d. limit coverage to a 24-month period; and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="46" slineno="1-28" display="tab"/><para/>e. align current bariatric surgery pilot program coaching and other participation <ln numlevel="1" lineno="47" slineno="1-29"/>requirements to also apply to the alternative GLP-1 treatment pathway;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="48" slineno="1-30" display="tab"/>(3) permit medically qualified members who enter the Weight Management and Obesity <ln numlevel="1" lineno="49" slineno="1-31"/>Pilot Program to make a one-time choice between bariatric surgery and the alternative GLP-1 <ln numlevel="1" lineno="50" slineno="1-32"/>treatment pathway, providing that if a member discontinues use of GLP-1 treatment within six <ln numlevel="1" lineno="51" slineno="1-33"/>months, the member may participate in the pilot program for bariatric surgery;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="52" slineno="1-34" display="tab"/>(4) administer the Weight Management and Obesity Pilot Program to stay within the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="53" slineno="1-35"/>adjusted annual budget; and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="54" slineno="1-36" display="tab"/>(5) before December 1, 2026, and each year thereafter until 2028, report to the Health and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="55" slineno="1-37"/>Human Services Interim Committee on the results of the Weight Management and Obesity <ln numlevel="1" lineno="56" slineno="1-38"/>Pilot Program.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="57" slineno="1-39" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that a copy of this resolution be sent to the Public <ln numlevel="1" lineno="58" slineno="1-40"/>Employees' Benefit and Insurance Program.</amend><sectionText/></section></bsec></bdy><foot><rev><tm>2-20-26 10:25 AM</tm></rev></foot></leg>