<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-16"?>
<leg xml:space="preserve" billnum="HCR004" sponsor="Michael J. Petersen" designation="HCR" otherSponsor="Keven J. Stratton" otherHouse="Senate" sess="2026GS" fileno="2026FL0231" date="01-06-26" printDate="01-08 14:43" subVer="0" minVer="0" office="LEGISLATIVE GENERAL COUNSEL" actionDate="" impact="reso"><info><nextbuid>2</nextbuid><aminfo anum="0" effdate="01/01/1800"><seclist><sect action="E" src="reso" buid="1" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" mtype="section" effdate="01/01/1800"/></seclist></aminfo></info><tbox><sinfo/><st numlevel="1" lineno="1" slineno="0-1">Concurrent Resolution Regarding Religious Freedom</st><sessionhead>2026 GENERAL SESSION</sessionhead><statehead>STATE OF UTAH</statehead><sponsorhead>Chief Sponsor: Michael J. Petersen</sponsorhead><otherSponsorhead>Senate Sponsor: Keven J. Stratton</otherSponsorhead></tbox><lt numlevel="1" lineno="2" slineno="0-2"><lthead lineno="3">LONG TITLE</lthead><gdhead lineno="4">General Description:</gdhead><gd numlevel="1" lineno="5" slineno="0-5">This resolution supports and encourages practices that exemplify religious freedom in <ln numlevel="1" lineno="6" slineno="0-6"/>public spaces.</gd><hphead lineno="7">Highlighted Provisions:</hphead><hp numlevel="1" lineno="8" slineno="0-8">This resolution:<hl numlevel="1" lineno="9" slineno="0-9" level="1">acknowledges the historical context that supports the inclusion of religion in government <ln numlevel="1" lineno="10" slineno="0-10"/>and education;</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="11" slineno="0-11" level="1">supports the right of public school students and teachers to openly express their faith;</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="12" slineno="0-12" level="1">encourages the accommodation of religious observances in government and community <ln numlevel="1" lineno="13" slineno="0-13"/>settings;</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="14" slineno="0-14" level="1">supports the protection of religious symbols in public spaces; and</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="15" slineno="0-15" level="1">encourages the fostering of respectful dialogue among diverse faith traditions.</hl></hp><moni numlevel="1" lineno="16" slineno="0-16" display="none">Money Appropriated in this Bill:</moni><moniNone lineno="17">None</moniNone><oc numlevel="1" lineno="18" slineno="0-18">Other Special Clauses:</oc><ocNone lineno="19">None</ocNone></lt><enacthead lineno="20"/><enact numlevel="1" lineno="21" slineno="0-21">Be it resolved by the Legislature of the state of Utah, the Governor concurring therein:</enact><bdy><bsec buid="1" type="enact" src="reso" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" numlevel="1" lineno="22" slineno="1-1" sn="1"><section type="enact" display="false" src="reso"><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="1" groupid="1" style="X" owner="jchristopherson" level="1" amendtag="both">WHEREAS, the Declaration of Independence states, "We hold these truths to be <ln numlevel="1" lineno="23" slineno="1-2"/>self-evident, that all men are created equal, that they are endowed by their Creator with certain <ln numlevel="1" lineno="24" slineno="1-3"/>unalienable rights, that among these are Life, Liberty, and the pursuit of Happiness. That to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="25" slineno="1-4"/>secure these rights, Governments are instituted among Men...";<eol numlevel="1" lineno="26" slineno="1-5" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, religious freedom is a foundational principle of democratic society and a <ln numlevel="1" lineno="27" slineno="1-6"/>fundamental human right recognized by the First Amendment of the United States <ln numlevel="1" lineno="28" slineno="1-7"/>Constitution;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="29" slineno="1-8" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, in Thomas Jefferson's description of the Virginia Statute for Religious <ln numlevel="1" lineno="30" slineno="1-9"/>Freedom of 1786, he established that religious freedom was meant to comprehend, within the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="31" slineno="1-10"/>mantle of its protection, Americans of every denomination;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="32" slineno="1-11" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, in a 1790 letter to a Jewish congregation in Newport, Rhode Island, George <ln numlevel="1" lineno="33" slineno="1-12"/>Washington wrote that the new nation he was helping build would give "to bigotry no <ln numlevel="1" lineno="34" slineno="1-13"/>sanction, to persecution no assistance," and that "everyone shall sit in safety under his own <ln numlevel="1" lineno="35" slineno="1-14"/>vine and fig tree and there shall be none to make him afraid.";<eol numlevel="1" lineno="36" slineno="1-15" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, Benjamin Franklin's creed, contained in his 1790 letter to Ezra Stiles, states <ln numlevel="1" lineno="37" slineno="1-16"/>that "God [is the] creator of the universe. That he governs it by his Providence. That he ought <ln numlevel="1" lineno="38" slineno="1-17"/>to be worshiped.";<eol numlevel="1" lineno="39" slineno="1-18" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, in his 1796 farewell address to the people of the United States, George <ln numlevel="1" lineno="40" slineno="1-19"/>Washington said, "Of all the dispositions and habits which lead to political prosperity, religion <ln numlevel="1" lineno="41" slineno="1-20"/>and morality are indispensable supports.";<eol numlevel="1" lineno="42" slineno="1-21" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, John Adams taught "Our Constitution was made only for a moral and religious <ln numlevel="1" lineno="43" slineno="1-22"/>People. It is wholly inadequate to the government of any other.";<eol numlevel="1" lineno="44" slineno="1-23" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the New England Primer, first published in 1690, and utilized across four <ln numlevel="1" lineno="45" slineno="1-24"/>centuries, included the Ten Commandments and other theological teachings to instruct <ln numlevel="1" lineno="46" slineno="1-25"/>children to read and write;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="47" slineno="1-26" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, Utah Constitution, Article I, Section 4, declares that the rights of conscience <ln numlevel="1" lineno="48" slineno="1-27"/>shall never be infringed;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="49" slineno="1-28" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, in 1971, the Supreme Court in Lemon v. Kurtzman created the "Lemon Test" <ln numlevel="1" lineno="50" slineno="1-29"/>that included a requirement of a secular legislative purpose, resulting in that case being cited <ln numlevel="1" lineno="51" slineno="1-30"/>over 7,000 times in subsequent federal cases between the years 1971 and 2019;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="52" slineno="1-31" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, in 2022, the Supreme Court overturned the "Lemon Test" in Shurtleff v. <ln numlevel="1" lineno="53" slineno="1-32"/>Boston declaring that the Lemon decision was "issued during a bygone era when this court <ln numlevel="1" lineno="54" slineno="1-33"/>took a more freewheeling approach to interpreting legal texts...";<eol numlevel="1" lineno="55" slineno="1-34" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, in 2019, the Supreme Court declared in American Legion v. American <ln numlevel="1" lineno="56" slineno="1-35"/>Humanist Association that longstanding religiously expressive monuments, symbols, and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="57" slineno="1-36"/>practices require a strong presumption of constitutionality; and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="58" slineno="1-37" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, in 2022, the Supreme Court declared in Kennedy v. Bremerton that "The [free <ln numlevel="1" lineno="59" slineno="1-38"/>exercise] clause protects not only the right to harbor religious beliefs inwardly and secretly. It <ln numlevel="1" lineno="60" slineno="1-39"/>does perhaps its most important work by protecting the ability of those who hold religious <ln numlevel="1" lineno="61" slineno="1-40"/>beliefs of all kinds to live out their faiths in daily life through the performance of (or <ln numlevel="1" lineno="62" slineno="1-41"/>abstention from) physical acts.":<eol numlevel="1" lineno="63" slineno="1-42" display="tab"/>NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED that the Legislature of the state of Utah, the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="64" slineno="1-43"/>Governor concurring therein, supports and encourages practices that exemplify religious <ln numlevel="1" lineno="65" slineno="1-44"/>freedom in public spaces, including the right of public school students and teachers to openly <ln numlevel="1" lineno="66" slineno="1-45"/>express their faith, accommodation of religious observances in government and community <ln numlevel="1" lineno="67" slineno="1-46"/>settings, the protection of religious symbols in public spaces, and the fostering of respectful <ln numlevel="1" lineno="68" slineno="1-47"/>dialogue among diverse faith traditions to uphold the foundational principles of religious <ln numlevel="1" lineno="69" slineno="1-48"/>liberty enshrined in the United States Constitution.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="70" slineno="1-49" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that the Legislature and the Governor support protecting <ln numlevel="1" lineno="71" slineno="1-50"/>religious freedom and allowing individuals of all faiths to participate freely in public life.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="72" slineno="1-51" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that copies of this resolution be sent to each county <ln numlevel="1" lineno="73" slineno="1-52"/>legislative body, municipal legislative body, and local school board within the state.</amend><sectionText/></section></bsec></bdy><foot><rev><tm>1-6-26 12:16 PM</tm></rev></foot></leg>