<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-16"?>
<leg xml:space="preserve" billnum="HJR012" sponsor="Nicholeen P. Peck" designation="HJR" otherSponsor="Keven J. Stratton" otherHouse="Senate" subNumber="03" subSponsor="Keven J. Stratton" sess="2026GS" fileno="2026FL1249" date="3/6/2026 08:03:163" printDate="03-06 08:57" subVer="3" minVer="0" office="LEGISLATIVE GENERAL COUNSEL" actionDate="" impact="reso"><info><nextbuid>2</nextbuid><aminfo anum="0" effdate="01/01/1800"><seclist><sect action="E" src="reso" buid="1" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" mtype="section" effdate="01/01/1800"/></seclist></aminfo></info><tbox><sinfo><nextpairid>0</nextpairid></sinfo><st numlevel="1" lineno="1" slineno="0-1">Joint Resolution Supporting Devolution of Power from the U.S. Department of Education to the States</st><sessionhead>2026 GENERAL SESSION</sessionhead><statehead>STATE OF UTAH</statehead><sponsorhead>Chief Sponsor: Nicholeen P. Peck</sponsorhead><otherSponsorhead>Senate Sponsor: Keven J. Stratton</otherSponsorhead></tbox><lt numlevel="1" lineno="2" slineno="0-2"><lthead lineno="3">LONG TITLE</lthead><gdhead lineno="4">General Description:</gdhead><gd numlevel="1" lineno="5" slineno="0-5">This resolution supports federal efforts to eliminate the United States Department of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="6" slineno="0-6"/>Education.</gd><hphead lineno="7">Highlighted Provisions:</hphead><hp numlevel="1" lineno="8" slineno="0-8">This resolution:<hl numlevel="1" lineno="9" slineno="0-9" level="1">identifies the federal overreach of the United States Department of Education resulting in <ln numlevel="1" lineno="10" slineno="0-10"/>burdensome regulations and significant economic and educational costs to students and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="11" slineno="0-11"/>the states;</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="12" slineno="0-12" level="1">supports President Trump's desire to move control of federal education dollars to the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="13" slineno="0-13"/>states to promote better outcomes in the education of students; and</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="14" slineno="0-14" level="1">urges the United States Congress to cooperate in the efforts to move education funding to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="15" slineno="0-15"/>the states.</hl></hp><moni numlevel="1" lineno="16" slineno="0-16" display="none">Money Appropriated in this Bill:</moni><moniNone lineno="17">None</moniNone><oc numlevel="1" lineno="18" slineno="0-18">Other Special Clauses:</oc><ocNone lineno="19">None</ocNone></lt><enacthead lineno="20"/><enact numlevel="1" lineno="21" slineno="0-21">Be it resolved by the Legislature of the state of Utah:</enact><bdy><bsec buid="1" type="enact" src="reso" uid="RESO" sort="00000R" numlevel="1" lineno="22" slineno="1-1" sn="1"><section type="enact" display="false" src="reso"><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="1" groupid="1" style="X" owner="jchristopherson" level="1" amendtag="both">WHEREAS, the state of Utah has established in Section <xref depth="3" refnumber="53E-2-201">53E-2-201</xref> that the continuous <ln numlevel="1" lineno="23" slineno="1-2"/>cultivation of an informed and virtuous citizenry among succeeding generations is essential to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="24" slineno="1-3"/>the state and the nation;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="25" slineno="1-4" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the Tenth Amendment to the United States Constitution reserves to the states <ln numlevel="1" lineno="26" slineno="1-5"/>any powers not delegated to the federal government;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="27" slineno="1-6" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the United States Constitution does not give the federal government any <ln numlevel="1" lineno="28" slineno="1-7"/>authority or responsibility regarding education;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="29" slineno="1-8" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, since its creation in 1979, the United States Department of Education has <ln numlevel="1" lineno="30" slineno="1-9"/>significantly overreached through burdensome regulations and one-size-fits-all mandates;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="31" slineno="1-10" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, despite an annual budget of $60 billion and another $276 billion in one-time <ln numlevel="1" lineno="32" slineno="1-11"/>spending for COVID-19 recovery efforts, the appropriation of significant funding has not <ln numlevel="1" lineno="33" slineno="1-12"/>resulted in a considerable increase in measurable educational outcomes for students;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="34" slineno="1-13" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, federal inefficiencies are obvious where 4th and 8th grade reading scores have <ln numlevel="1" lineno="35" slineno="1-14"/>remained the same as they were in the early 1990s when federal measurements first began;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="36" slineno="1-15" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, states and local communities are best suited to administer the public education <ln numlevel="1" lineno="37" slineno="1-16"/>system because local governments are directly accountable to the students and parents within <ln numlevel="1" lineno="38" slineno="1-17"/>the community;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="39" slineno="1-18" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, state and local knowledge of students' educational needs is fundamental to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="40" slineno="1-19"/>developing the curriculum and policies that reflect local values and priorities;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="41" slineno="1-20" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, direct appropriations of funds to the state would provide necessary resources <ln numlevel="1" lineno="42" slineno="1-21"/>to provide for the educational needs of the students of the state;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="43" slineno="1-22" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, President Trump has expressed a desire to rightfully put the states back in <ln numlevel="1" lineno="44" slineno="1-23"/>charge of education; and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="45" slineno="1-24" display="tab"/>WHEREAS, the elimination of the United States Department of Education is not only a <ln numlevel="1" lineno="46" slineno="1-25"/>constitutional necessity but will also ensure that taxpayer dollars are spent more efficiently and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="47" slineno="1-26"/>lead to better student outcomes:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="48" slineno="1-27" display="tab"/>NOW, THEREFORE, BE IT RESOLVED that the Legislature of state of Utah supports <ln numlevel="1" lineno="49" slineno="1-28"/>federal efforts to eliminate the United States Department of Education and strongly urges the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="50" slineno="1-29"/>United States Congress to fully cooperate with these efforts.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="51" slineno="1-30" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that Utah is the best managed state in the nation and can <ln numlevel="1" lineno="52" slineno="1-31"/>manage its affairs more affordably, effectively, and efficiently than the federal government.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="53" slineno="1-32" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that Utah has demonstrated time and again the ability to be <ln numlevel="1" lineno="54" slineno="1-33"/>an effective and prudent steward of taxpayers' hard earned dollars.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="55" slineno="1-34" display="tab"/>BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that Utah stands uniquely prepared to prove the concept of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="56" slineno="1-35"/>allowing the states to manage federal tax dollars for the public education system.</amend><sectionText/></section></bsec></bdy><foot><rev><tm>3-6-26 8:57 AM</tm></rev></foot></leg>