<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-16"?>
<leg xml:space="preserve" billnum="SJR010" sponsor="Michael K. McKell" designation="SJR" otherSponsor="Casey Snider" otherHouse="House" subNumber="02" subSponsor="Karianne Lisonbee" sess="2026GS" fileno="2026FL0284" date="3/3/2026 17:03:750" printDate="03-03 17:28" subVer="2" minVer="0" office="LEGISLATIVE GENERAL COUNSEL" actionDate="" impact="reso"><info><nextbuid>8</nextbuid><aminfo anum="0" effdate="01/01/1800"><seclist><sect src="uncod" untype="rule" buid="2" uid="URC00000018" sort="URC00018" mtype="section" atype="A" effdate="01/01/1800">Rule 18</sect><sect src="uncod" untype="rule" buid="4" uid="URC000017.5" sort="URC017.5" mtype="section" atype="A" effdate="01/01/1800">Rule 17.5</sect><sect src="uncod" untype="effdate" buid="7" uid="EF0000" sort="UZEFF" mtype="uncod" effdate="01/01/1800"/></seclist></aminfo></info><tbox><sinfo><nextpairid>0</nextpairid></sinfo><st numlevel="1" lineno="1" slineno="0-1">Joint Resolution Amending Court Rules Regarding Jury Selection</st><sessionhead>2026 GENERAL SESSION</sessionhead><statehead>STATE OF UTAH</statehead><sponsorhead>Chief Sponsor: Michael K. McKell</sponsorhead><otherSponsorhead>House Sponsor: Casey Snider</otherSponsorhead></tbox><lt numlevel="1" lineno="2" slineno="0-2"><lthead lineno="3">LONG TITLE</lthead><gdhead lineno="4">General Description:</gdhead><gd numlevel="1" lineno="5" slineno="0-5">This resolution amends court rules regarding jury selection.</gd><hphead lineno="6">Highlighted Provisions:</hphead><hp numlevel="1" lineno="7" slineno="0-7">This resolution:<hl numlevel="1" lineno="8" slineno="0-8" level="1">amends Rule 17.5 of the Utah Rules of Criminal Procedure to address an exception for <ln numlevel="1" lineno="9" slineno="0-9"/>jury selection in a felony case;</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="10" slineno="0-10" level="1">amends Rule 18 of the Utah Rules of Criminal Procedure to address jury selection in a <ln numlevel="1" lineno="11" slineno="0-11"/>felony case; and</hl><hl numlevel="1" lineno="12" slineno="0-12" level="1">makes technical and conforming changes.</hl></hp><moni numlevel="1" lineno="13" slineno="0-13" display="none">Money Appropriated in this Bill:</moni><moniNone lineno="14">None</moniNone><oc numlevel="1" lineno="15" slineno="0-15">Other Special Clauses:<ocl type="effdate" sort="2" numlevel="1" lineno="16" slineno="0-16">This resolution provides a special effective date.</ocl></oc><pa type="criminal" numlevel="1" lineno="17" slineno="0-17">Utah Rules of Criminal Procedure Affected:<paamd numlevel="1" lineno="18" slineno="0-18"><snhead>AMENDS:</snhead><sn num="Rule 17.5" src="uncod" uid="URC000017.5" buid="4" sort="URC017.5" numlevel="1" lineno="19" slineno="0-19"><bold>Rule 17.5</bold>, Utah Rules of Criminal Procedure</sn><sn num="Rule 18" src="uncod" uid="URC00000018" buid="2" sort="URC00018" numlevel="1" lineno="20" slineno="0-20"><bold>Rule 18</bold>, Utah Rules of Criminal Procedure</sn></paamd></pa></lt><enacthead lineno="21"/><enact numlevel="1" lineno="22" slineno="0-22">Be it resolved by the Legislature of the state of Utah, two-thirds of all members elected to each <ln numlevel="1" lineno="23" slineno="0-23"/>of the two houses voting in favor thereof:<enactdesc numlevel="1" lineno="24" slineno="0-24">As provided in Utah Constitution Article VIII, Section 4, the Legislature may amend rules of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="25" slineno="0-25"/>procedure and evidence adopted by the Utah Supreme Court upon a two-thirds vote of all <ln numlevel="1" lineno="26" slineno="0-26"/>members of both houses of the Legislature:</enactdesc></enact><bdy><bsec buid="4" type="uncod" untype="rule" rtype="criminal" atype="amend" num="Rule 17.5" src="rule" uid="URC000017.5" sort="URC017.5" langlock="false" numlevel="1" lineno="27" slineno="1-1" sn="1"><section number="Rule 17.5" numlevel="1" lineno="28" slineno="1-2" type="uncod" untype="rule" atype="amend"><secline lineno="27">Section 1. <bold>Rule 17.5</bold>, Utah Rules of Criminal Procedure is amended to read:</secline><catline lineno="28"><bold>Rule 17.5<parens/>. In-person, remote, and hybrid hearings; request for different format.</bold></catline><sectionText lineno="29"><para/>(a) <bold>Definitions.</bold><eol numlevel="1" lineno="30" slineno="1-4" display="tab"/><para/>(1) "Participant" means a party, a participating victim, or an attorney for a party or <ln numlevel="1" lineno="31" slineno="1-5"/>participating victim.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="32" slineno="1-6" display="tab"/><para/>(2) "In-person" means a participant will be physically present in the courtroom.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="33" slineno="1-7" display="tab"/><para/>(3) "In-person hearing" means a hearing where all participants appear in person.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="34" slineno="1-8" display="tab"/><para/>(4) "Remote" or "remotely" means a participant will appear by video conference or other <ln numlevel="1" lineno="35" slineno="1-9"/>electronic means approved by the court.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="36" slineno="1-10" display="tab"/><para/>(5) "Remote hearing" means no participants will be physically present in the courtroom <ln numlevel="1" lineno="37" slineno="1-11"/>and all participants will appear remotely.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="38" slineno="1-12" display="tab"/><para/>(6) "Hybrid hearing" means a hearing at which some participants appear in person and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="39" slineno="1-13"/>others appear remotely.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="40" slineno="1-14" display="tab"/>(b) <bold>Setting hearing format; factors to consider.</bold> <amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="3" groupid="3" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">The</amend><amendoutend style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="2" groupid="2" style="1" owner="ahaskell" level="1" amendtag="both" space="true">Except as provided in Rule 18(b), the</amend> <ln numlevel="1" lineno="41" slineno="1-15"/>court has discretion to set a hearing as an in-person hearing, a remote hearing, or a hybrid <ln numlevel="1" lineno="42" slineno="1-16"/>hearing. In determining which format to use for a hearing, the court will consider:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="43" slineno="1-17" display="tab"/><para/>(1) the preference of the participants, if known;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="44" slineno="1-18" display="tab"/><para/>(2) the anticipated hearing length;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="45" slineno="1-19" display="tab"/><para/>(3) the number of participants;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="46" slineno="1-20" display="tab"/><para/>(4) the burden on a participant of appearing in person compared to appearing remotely, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="47" slineno="1-21"/>including time and economic impacts;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="48" slineno="1-22" display="tab"/><para/>(5) the complexity of issues to be addressed;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="49" slineno="1-23" display="tab"/><para/>(6) whether and to what extent documentary or testimonial evidence is likely to be <ln numlevel="1" lineno="50" slineno="1-24"/>presented;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="51" slineno="1-25" display="tab"/><para/>(7) the availability of adequate technology to accomplish the hearing's purpose; <eol numlevel="1" lineno="52" slineno="1-26" display="tab"/><para/>(8) the availability of language interpretation or accommodations for communication <ln numlevel="1" lineno="53" slineno="1-27"/>with individuals with disabilities;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="54" slineno="1-28" display="tab"/><para/>(9) the possibility that the court may order a party, who is not already in custody, into <ln numlevel="1" lineno="55" slineno="1-29"/>custody;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="56" slineno="1-30" display="tab"/><para/>(10) the preference of the incarcerating custodian where a party is incarcerated, if the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="57" slineno="1-31"/>hearing does not implicate significant constitutional rights; and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="58" slineno="1-32" display="tab"/><para/>(11) any other factor, based on the specific facts and circumstances of the case or the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="59" slineno="1-33"/>court's calendar, that the court deems relevant.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="60" slineno="1-34" display="tab"/>(c) <bold>Request to appear by a different format.</bold><eol numlevel="1" lineno="61" slineno="1-35" display="tab"/><para/>(1) <bold>Manner of request.</bold> A participant may request that the court allow the participant or a <ln numlevel="1" lineno="62" slineno="1-36"/>witness to appear at a hearing by a different format than that set by the court. Any request must <ln numlevel="1" lineno="63" slineno="1-37"/>be made verbally during a hearing, by email, by letter, or by written motion, and the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="64" slineno="1-38"/>participant must state the reason for the request. If a participant is represented by an attorney, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="65" slineno="1-39"/>all requests must be made by the attorney.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="66" slineno="1-40" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(A) <bold>Email and letter requests.</bold><eol numlevel="1" lineno="67" slineno="1-41" display="tab"/><para/><tab/><tab/>(i) An email or letter request must be copied on all parties;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="68" slineno="1-42" display="tab"/><para/><tab/><tab/>(ii) An email or letter request must include in the subject line, "REQUEST TO <ln numlevel="1" lineno="69" slineno="1-43"/>APPEAR IN PERSON, Case ___________" or "REQUEST TO APPEAR REMOTELY, Case <ln numlevel="1" lineno="70" slineno="1-44"/>_________;" and<eol numlevel="1" lineno="71" slineno="1-45" display="tab"/><para/><tab/><tab/>(iii) An email request must be sent to the court's email address, which may be <ln numlevel="1" lineno="72" slineno="1-46"/>obtained from the court clerk.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="73" slineno="1-47" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(B) <bold>Request by written motion.</bold> If making a request by written motion, the motion <ln numlevel="1" lineno="74" slineno="1-48"/>must succinctly state the grounds for the request and be accompanied by a request to submit <ln numlevel="1" lineno="75" slineno="1-49"/>for decision and a proposed order. The motion need not be accompanied by a supporting <ln numlevel="1" lineno="76" slineno="1-50"/>memorandum. <eol numlevel="1" lineno="77" slineno="1-51" display="tab"/><para/>(2) <bold>Timing.</bold> All requests, except those made verbally during a hearing, must be sent to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="78" slineno="1-52"/>the court at least seven days before the hearing unless there are exigent circumstances or the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="79" slineno="1-53"/>hearing was set less than seven days before the hearing date, in which cases the request must <ln numlevel="1" lineno="80" slineno="1-54"/>be made as soon as reasonably possible.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="81" slineno="1-55" display="tab"/>(d) <bold>Resolution of the request.</bold><eol numlevel="1" lineno="82" slineno="1-56" display="tab"/><para/>(1) <bold>Timing and manner of resolution. </bold>The court may rule on a request under paragraph <ln numlevel="1" lineno="83" slineno="1-57"/>(c) without awaiting a response. The court may rule on the request in open court, by email, by <ln numlevel="1" lineno="84" slineno="1-58"/>minute entry, or by written order. If the request is made by email, the court will make a record <ln numlevel="1" lineno="85" slineno="1-59"/>of the request if the request is denied.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="86" slineno="1-60" display="tab"/><para/>(2) <bold>Court's accommodation of participant's preference; factors to consider. </bold>The court <ln numlevel="1" lineno="87" slineno="1-61"/>will accommodate a timely request unless the court makes, on the record, a finding of good <ln numlevel="1" lineno="88" slineno="1-62"/>cause to order the participant to appear in the format originally noticed. The court may find <ln numlevel="1" lineno="89" slineno="1-63"/>good cause to deny a request based on:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="90" slineno="1-64" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(A) a constitutional or statutory right that requires a particular manner of appearance <ln numlevel="1" lineno="91" slineno="1-65"/>or a significant possibility that such a right would be impermissibly diminished or infringed by <ln numlevel="1" lineno="92" slineno="1-66"/>appearing remotely;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="93" slineno="1-67" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(B) a concern for a participant's or witness's safety, well-being, or specific situational <ln numlevel="1" lineno="94" slineno="1-68"/>needs;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="95" slineno="1-69" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(C) a prior technological challenge in the case that unreasonably contributed to delay <ln numlevel="1" lineno="96" slineno="1-70"/>or a compromised record;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="97" slineno="1-71" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(D) a prior failure to demonstrate appropriate court decorum, including attempting to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="98" slineno="1-72"/>participate from a location that is not conducive to accomplishing the purpose of the hearing;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="99" slineno="1-73" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(E) a prior failure to appear for a hearing of which the participant had notice; <eol numlevel="1" lineno="100" slineno="1-74" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(F) the possibility that the court <amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="6" groupid="6" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="start">m </amend><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="7" groupid="7" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="end">ay</amend><amendoutend style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="5" groupid="5" style="1" owner="ahaskell" level="1" amendtag="both" space="true">may</amend> order a party, who is not already in <ln numlevel="1" lineno="101" slineno="1-75"/>custody, into custody;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="102" slineno="1-76" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(G) the preference of the incarcerating custodian where a party is incarcerated, if the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="103" slineno="1-77"/>hearing does not implicate significant constitutional rights;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="104" slineno="1-78" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(H) a participant's involvement in a problem-solving court;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="105" slineno="1-79" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(I) an agreement or any objection of the parties;<eol numlevel="1" lineno="106" slineno="1-80" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(J) the court's determination that the consequential nature of a specific hearing <ln numlevel="1" lineno="107" slineno="1-81"/>requires all participants to appear in person; or<eol numlevel="1" lineno="108" slineno="1-82" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(K) the capacity of the court, including but not limited to the required technology <ln numlevel="1" lineno="109" slineno="1-83"/>equipment, staff, or security, to accommodate the request.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="110" slineno="1-84" display="tab"/><para/>(3) <bold>Effect on other participants. </bold>The preference of one participant, and the court's <ln numlevel="1" lineno="111" slineno="1-85"/>accommodation of that preference, does not:<eol numlevel="1" lineno="112" slineno="1-86" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(A) change the format of the hearing for any other participant unless otherwise <ln numlevel="1" lineno="113" slineno="1-87"/>ordered by the court; or<eol numlevel="1" lineno="114" slineno="1-88" display="tab"/><para/><tab/>(B) affect any other participant's opportunity to make a timely request to appear by a <ln numlevel="1" lineno="115" slineno="1-89"/>different format or the court's consideration of that request.</sectionText></section></bsec><bsec buid="2" type="uncod" untype="rule" rtype="criminal" atype="amend" num="Rule 18" src="rule" uid="URC00000018" sort="URC00018" langlock="false" numlevel="1" lineno="116" slineno="2-1" sn="2"><section number="Rule 18" numlevel="1" lineno="117" slineno="2-2" type="uncod" untype="rule" atype="amend"><secline lineno="116">Section 2. <bold>Rule 18</bold>, Utah Rules of Criminal Procedure is amended to read:</secline><catline lineno="117"><bold>Rule 18<parens/>. Selection of the jury.</bold></catline><sectionText lineno="118"><para/>(a) <bold>Method of selection.</bold> The judge shall determine the method of selecting the jury and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="119" slineno="2-4"/>notify the parties at a pretrial conference or otherwise prior to trial. The following procedures <ln numlevel="1" lineno="120" slineno="2-5"/>for selection are not exclusive.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="121" slineno="2-6" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="3" groupid="3" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(a)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(1) <bold>Strike and replace method</bold>. The court shall summon the number of the jurors that <ln numlevel="1" lineno="122" slineno="2-7"/>are to try the cause plus such an additional number as will allow for any alternates, for all <ln numlevel="1" lineno="123" slineno="2-8"/>peremptory challenges permitted, and for all challenges for cause granted. At the direction of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="124" slineno="2-9"/>the judge, the clerk shall call jurors in random order. The judge may hear and determine <ln numlevel="1" lineno="125" slineno="2-10"/>challenges for cause during the course of questioning or at the end thereof. The judge may and, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="126" slineno="2-11"/>at the request of any party, shall hear and determine challenges for cause outside the hearing of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="127" slineno="2-12"/>the jurors. After each challenge for cause sustained, another juror shall be called to fill the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="128" slineno="2-13"/>vacancy, and any such new juror may be challenged for cause. When the challenges for cause <ln numlevel="1" lineno="129" slineno="2-14"/>are completed, the clerk shall provide a list of the jurors remaining, and each side, beginning <ln numlevel="1" lineno="130" slineno="2-15"/>with the prosecution, shall indicate thereon its peremptory challenge to one juror at a time in <ln numlevel="1" lineno="131" slineno="2-16"/>regular turn, as the court may direct, until all peremptory challenges are exhausted or waived. <ln numlevel="1" lineno="132" slineno="2-17"/>The clerk shall then call the remaining jurors, or so many of them as shall be necessary to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="133" slineno="2-18"/>constitute the jury, including any alternate jurors, and the persons whose names are so called <ln numlevel="1" lineno="134" slineno="2-19"/>shall constitute the jury. If alternate jurors have been selected, the last jurors called shall be the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="135" slineno="2-20"/>alternates, unless otherwise ordered by the court prior to voir dire.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="136" slineno="2-21" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="6" groupid="6" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(a)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(2) <bold>Struck method</bold>. The court shall summon the number of jurors that are to try the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="137" slineno="2-22"/>cause plus such an additional number as will allow for any alternates, for all peremptory <ln numlevel="1" lineno="138" slineno="2-23"/>challenges permitted and for all challenges for cause granted. At the direction of the judge, the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="139" slineno="2-24"/>clerk shall call jurors in random order. The judge may hear and determine challenges for cause <ln numlevel="1" lineno="140" slineno="2-25"/>during the course of questioning or at the end thereof. The judge may and, at the request of any <ln numlevel="1" lineno="141" slineno="2-26"/>party, shall hear and determine challenges for cause outside the hearing of the jurors. When the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="142" slineno="2-27"/>challenges for cause are completed, the clerk shall provide a list of the jurors remaining, and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="143" slineno="2-28"/>each side, beginning with the prosecution, shall indicate thereon its peremptory challenge to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="144" slineno="2-29"/>one juror at a time in regular turn until all peremptory challenges are exhausted or waived. The <ln numlevel="1" lineno="145" slineno="2-30"/>clerk shall then call the remaining jurors, or so many of them as shall be necessary to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="146" slineno="2-31"/>constitute the jury, including any alternate jurors, and the persons whose names are so called <ln numlevel="1" lineno="147" slineno="2-32"/>shall constitute the jury. If alternate jurors have been selected, the last jurors called shall be the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="148" slineno="2-33"/>alternates, unless otherwise ordered by the court prior to voir dire.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="149" slineno="2-34" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="7" groupid="7" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(a)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(3) In courts using lists of prospective jurors generated in random order by computer, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="150" slineno="2-35"/>the clerk may call the jurors in that random order.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="151" slineno="2-36" display="tab"/>(b) <bold>Examination of prospective jurors.</bold> <amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="1" groupid="1" style="1" owner="ahaskell" level="1" amendtag="both"><eol numlevel="1" lineno="152" slineno="2-37" display="tab"/>(1) (i) In a felony case, the court must conduct jury selection in person at the place of trial <ln numlevel="1" lineno="153" slineno="2-38"/>unless both parties agree, on the record, that jury selection be conducted virtually.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="154" slineno="2-39" display="tab"/><para/>(ii) When jury selection is conducted in person under paragraph (b)(1)(i), all prospective <ln numlevel="1" lineno="155" slineno="2-40"/>jurors must appear in person for examination.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="156" slineno="2-41" display="tab"/>(2) </amend>The court may permit counsel or the defendant to conduct the examination of the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="157" slineno="2-42"/>prospective jurors or may itself conduct the examination. In the latter event, the court may <ln numlevel="1" lineno="158" slineno="2-43"/>permit counsel or the defendant to supplement the examination by such further inquiry as <amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="36" groupid="36" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">it</amend><amendoutend style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="35" groupid="35" style="1" owner="ahaskell" level="1" amendtag="both" space="true"><ln numlevel="1" lineno="159" slineno="2-44"/>the court</amend> deems proper, or may itself submit to the prospective jurors additional questions <ln numlevel="1" lineno="160" slineno="2-45"/>requested by counsel or the defendant. <amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="33" groupid="33" style="1" owner="ahaskell" level="1" amendtag="both"><eol numlevel="1" lineno="161" slineno="2-46" display="tab"/>(3) </amend>Prior to examining the jurors, the court may make a preliminary statement of the case. <ln numlevel="1" lineno="162" slineno="2-47"/>The court may permit the parties or their attorneys to make a preliminary statement of the case, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="163" slineno="2-48"/>and notify the parties in advance of trial.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="164" slineno="2-49" display="tab"/>(c) <bold>Challenges to panel or individuals.</bold> A challenge may be made to the panel or to an <ln numlevel="1" lineno="165" slineno="2-50"/>individual juror.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="166" slineno="2-51" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="9" groupid="9" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(c)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(1) The panel is a list of jurors called to serve at a particular court or for the trial of a <ln numlevel="1" lineno="167" slineno="2-52"/>particular action. A challenge to the panel is an objection made to all jurors summoned and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="168" slineno="2-53"/>may be taken by either party.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="169" slineno="2-54" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="10" groupid="10" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(c)(1)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(i) A challenge to the panel can be founded only on a material departure from the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="170" slineno="2-55"/>procedure prescribed with respect to the selection, drawing, summoning and return of the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="171" slineno="2-56"/>panel.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="172" slineno="2-57" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="11" groupid="11" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(c)(1)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(ii) The challenge to the panel shall be taken before the jury is sworn and shall be in <ln numlevel="1" lineno="173" slineno="2-58"/>writing or made upon the record. It shall specifically set forth the facts constituting the grounds <ln numlevel="1" lineno="174" slineno="2-59"/>of the challenge.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="175" slineno="2-60" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="12" groupid="12" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(c)(1)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(iii) If a challenge to the panel is opposed by the adverse party, a hearing may be <ln numlevel="1" lineno="176" slineno="2-61"/>had to try any question of fact upon which the challenge is based. The jurors challenged, and <ln numlevel="1" lineno="177" slineno="2-62"/>any other persons, may be called as witnesses at the hearing thereon.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="178" slineno="2-63" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="13" groupid="13" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(c)(1)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(iv) The court shall decide the challenge. If the challenge to the panel is allowed, the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="179" slineno="2-64"/>court shall discharge the jury so far as the trial in question is concerned. If a challenge is <ln numlevel="1" lineno="180" slineno="2-65"/>denied, the court shall direct the selection of jurors to proceed.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="181" slineno="2-66" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="14" groupid="14" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(c)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(2) A challenge to an individual juror may be either peremptory or for cause. A <ln numlevel="1" lineno="182" slineno="2-67"/>challenge to an individual juror may be made only before the jury is sworn to try the action, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="183" slineno="2-68"/>except the court may, for good cause, permit it to be made after the juror is sworn but before <ln numlevel="1" lineno="184" slineno="2-69"/>any of the evidence is presented. In challenges for cause the rules relating to challenges to a <ln numlevel="1" lineno="185" slineno="2-70"/>panel and hearings thereon shall apply. All challenges for cause shall be taken first by the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="186" slineno="2-71"/>prosecution and then by the defense alternately. Challenges for cause shall be completed <ln numlevel="1" lineno="187" slineno="2-72"/>before peremptory challenges are taken.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="188" slineno="2-73" display="tab"/>(d) <bold>Peremptory challenges.</bold> A peremptory challenge is an objection to a juror for which no <ln numlevel="1" lineno="189" slineno="2-74"/>reason need be given. In capital cases, each side is entitled to 10 peremptory challenges. In <ln numlevel="1" lineno="190" slineno="2-75"/>other felony cases each side is entitled to four peremptory challenges. In misdemeanor cases, <ln numlevel="1" lineno="191" slineno="2-76"/>each side is entitled to three peremptory challenges. If there is more than one defendant the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="192" slineno="2-77"/>court may allow the defendants additional peremptory challenges and permit them to be <ln numlevel="1" lineno="193" slineno="2-78"/>exercised separately or jointly.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="194" slineno="2-79" display="tab"/>(e) <bold>Challenges for cause.</bold> A challenge for cause is an objection to a particular juror and shall <ln numlevel="1" lineno="195" slineno="2-80"/>be heard and determined by the court. The juror challenged and any other person may be <ln numlevel="1" lineno="196" slineno="2-81"/>examined as a witness on the hearing of such challenge. A challenge for cause may be taken <ln numlevel="1" lineno="197" slineno="2-82"/>on one or more of the following grounds. On its own motion the court may remove a juror <ln numlevel="1" lineno="198" slineno="2-83"/>upon the same grounds.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="199" slineno="2-84" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="15" groupid="15" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(1) Want of any of the qualifications prescribed by law.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="200" slineno="2-85" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="17" groupid="17" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(2) Any mental or physical infirmity which renders one incapable of performing the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="201" slineno="2-86"/>duties of a juror.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="202" slineno="2-87" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="18" groupid="18" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(3) Consanguinity or affinity within the fourth degree to the person alleged to be <ln numlevel="1" lineno="203" slineno="2-88"/>injured by the offense charged, or on whose complaint the prosecution was instituted.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="204" slineno="2-89" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="19" groupid="19" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(4) The existence of any social, legal, business, fiduciary or other relationship between <ln numlevel="1" lineno="205" slineno="2-90"/>the prospective juror and any party, witness or person alleged to have been victimized or <ln numlevel="1" lineno="206" slineno="2-91"/>injured by the defendant, which relationship when viewed objectively, would suggest to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="207" slineno="2-92"/>reasonable minds that the prospective juror would be unable or unwilling to return a verdict <ln numlevel="1" lineno="208" slineno="2-93"/>which would be free of favoritism. A prospective juror shall not be disqualified solely because <ln numlevel="1" lineno="209" slineno="2-94"/>the juror is indebted to or employed by the state or a political subdivision thereof.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="210" slineno="2-95" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="20" groupid="20" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(5) Having been or being the party adverse to the defendant in a civil action, or having <ln numlevel="1" lineno="211" slineno="2-96"/>complained against or having been accused by the defendant in a criminal prosecution.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="212" slineno="2-97" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="21" groupid="21" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(6) Having served on the grand jury which found the indictment.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="213" slineno="2-98" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="22" groupid="22" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(7) Having served on a trial jury which has tried another person for the particular <ln numlevel="1" lineno="214" slineno="2-99"/>offense charged.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="215" slineno="2-100" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="23" groupid="23" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(8) Having been one of a jury formally sworn to try the same charge, and whose verdict <ln numlevel="1" lineno="216" slineno="2-101"/>was set aside, or which was discharged without a verdict after the case was submitted to it.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="217" slineno="2-102" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="24" groupid="24" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(9) Having served as a juror in a civil action brought against the defendant for the act <ln numlevel="1" lineno="218" slineno="2-103"/>charged as an offense.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="219" slineno="2-104" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="25" groupid="25" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(10) If the offense charged is punishable with death, the juror's views on capital <ln numlevel="1" lineno="220" slineno="2-105"/>punishment would prevent or substantially impair the performance of the juror's duties as a <ln numlevel="1" lineno="221" slineno="2-106"/>juror in accordance with the instructions of the court and the juror's oath in <amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="32" groupid="32" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">subsection (h)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="31" groupid="31" style="1" owner="ahaskell" level="1" amendtag="both" space="true"><ln numlevel="1" lineno="222" slineno="2-107"/>paragraph (g)</amend>.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="223" slineno="2-108" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="26" groupid="26" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(11) Because the juror is or, within one year preceding, has been engaged or interested <ln numlevel="1" lineno="224" slineno="2-109"/>in carrying on any business, calling or employment, the carrying on of which is a violation of <ln numlevel="1" lineno="225" slineno="2-110"/>law, where defendant is charged with a like offense.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="226" slineno="2-111" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="27" groupid="27" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(12) Because the juror has been a witness, either for or against the defendant on the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="227" slineno="2-112"/>preliminary examination or before the grand jury.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="228" slineno="2-113" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="28" groupid="28" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(13) Having formed or expressed an unqualified opinion or belief as to whether the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="229" slineno="2-114"/>defendant is guilty or not guilty of the offense charged.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="230" slineno="2-115" display="tab"/><amendoutstart style="2"/><amend anum="0" ea="erase" pairid="29" groupid="29" style="2" owner="ahaskell" level="1" deltag="both">(e)</amend><amendoutend style="2"/>(14) Conduct, responses, state of mind or other circumstances that reasonably lead the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="231" slineno="2-116"/>court to conclude the juror is not likely to act impartially. No person may serve as a juror, if <ln numlevel="1" lineno="232" slineno="2-117"/>challenged, unless the judge is convinced the juror can and will act impartially and fairly.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="233" slineno="2-118" display="tab"/>(f) <bold>Alternate jurors.</bold> The court may impanel alternate jurors to replace any jurors who are <ln numlevel="1" lineno="234" slineno="2-119"/>unable to perform or who are disqualified from performing their duties. Alternate jurors must <ln numlevel="1" lineno="235" slineno="2-120"/>have the same qualifications and be selected and sworn in the same manner as any other juror. <ln numlevel="1" lineno="236" slineno="2-121"/>If one or two alternate jurors are called, the prosecution and defense shall each have one <ln numlevel="1" lineno="237" slineno="2-122"/>additional peremptory challenge. If three or four alternate jurors are called, each side shall <ln numlevel="1" lineno="238" slineno="2-123"/>have two additional peremptory challenges. Alternate jurors replace jurors in the same <ln numlevel="1" lineno="239" slineno="2-124"/>sequence in which the alternates were selected. An alternate juror who replaces a juror has the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="240" slineno="2-125"/>same authority as the other jurors. The court may retain alternate jurors after the jury retires to <ln numlevel="1" lineno="241" slineno="2-126"/>deliberate. The court must ensure that a retained alternate does not discuss the case with <ln numlevel="1" lineno="242" slineno="2-127"/>anyone until that alternate replaces a juror or is discharged. If an alternate replaces a juror after <ln numlevel="1" lineno="243" slineno="2-128"/>deliberations have begun, the court must instruct the jury to begin its deliberations anew.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="244" slineno="2-129" display="tab"/>(g) <bold>Juror oath.</bold> When the jury is selected an oath shall be administered to the jurors, in <ln numlevel="1" lineno="245" slineno="2-130"/>substance, that they and each of them will well and truly try the matter in issue between the <ln numlevel="1" lineno="246" slineno="2-131"/>parties, and render a true verdict according to the evidence and the instructions of the court.</sectionText></section></bsec><bsec buid="7" type="uncod" untype="effdate" src="uncod" uid="EF0000" sort="UZEFF" langlock="false" numlevel="1" lineno="247" slineno="3-1" sn="3"><section type="uncod" untype="effdate" display="false" src="uncod"><secline lineno="247">Section 3.  <bold>Effective Date.</bold></secline><sectionText lineno="248"><amend anum="0" ea="amend" pairid="5" groupid="5" style="1" owner="ahaskell" level="1" amendtag="both">(1) In accordance with Utah Constitution, Article VIII, Section 4, the amendments in <ln numlevel="1" lineno="249" slineno="3-3"/>this resolution pass upon approval by a two-thirds vote of all members elected to each house.<eol numlevel="1" lineno="250" slineno="3-4" display="tab"/>(2) After passage of this resolution under Subsection (1), the amendments in this resolution <ln numlevel="1" lineno="251" slineno="3-5"/>take effect on January 1, 2027.</amend></sectionText></section></bsec></bdy><foot><rev><tm>3-3-26 5:28 PM</tm></rev></foot></leg>